this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at sc-radio.net
ski radio is brought to you by the IEEE
computer Society software Magazine
online at computer.org software
welcome to software engineering radio
and this is Priyanka raghavan
so we're going to be
going to be devops versus SRE the
difference is similarities how they can
work together for building successful
platforms Our Guest today is Ganesh Tata
who is the CTO and co-founder of Cortex
Ganesh has an active interest in the
areas of SRE and devops primarily from
spending many years working with both
these SRE and devops teams and now is a
co-founder of a company that develops a
platform for the latter I also saw that
Ganesh contributes a lot through this
magazine called devops.com where he's
written on topics such as metrics
reviews of Open Source libraries and
also discussing testing strategies so
welcome to the show Ganesh thanks so
much for having me at Essie Rito we've
actually done quite a lot of shows on
devops and SRE you know we've done a
show like for example episode 276 on
site reliability engineering episode 513
on devops practices to manage business
applications we also did an episode 457
on devops anti-patterns and then there
was also show episode 482 on
infrastructures S code so you know a ton
of stuff but we never looked at say the
differences between devops and SRE and I
thought this would be a perfect show to
do so that's why we're having you here
but before we jump into that I'm I'm
gonna actually dial it back and ask you
if you could just explain in your own
words what you think devops is for our
listeners you know I think about devops
it's there's obviously a lot of
confusion between like devops and SRE
and there's people that kind of do a
little bit of both and so it's
definitely a very open term and I think
the one thing that we always like to say
is like you don't understand just show
horn yourself into one or the other you
know there's a lot of people that
overlap but I think about devops is
literally the name right it's like
developer operations it's everything
around how do we increase entering
efficiency engineering productivity how
do we enable developers to operate and
work their best and that comes found to
everything from tooling to pipelines to
build systems to deployment systems to
all that kind of stuff I think is really
owned by the devops team and so anything
that when you think about like
development team operating their
services like that is exactly what
devops falls under right I believe and
so how about SRE then what could you see
about site reliability engineering yeah
I think it's interesting because when
you think about SRE they sometimes do a
lot of things that devops you would you
would think devops does you know around
like pipelines and things like that but
when I think about SRE it's more from
the lens of reliability like they're
thinking about are the processes that we
have in place leading to a better
outcomes when it comes to reliability
and uptime and those kinds of business
metrics and so sres is mostly focused on
defining and enforcing standards and
reliability building the tooling to make
make it easier for engineers to adopt
those practices and I think that's where
some of the overlap comes in we'll talk
about that later obviously but anything
that comes from a reliability or like
post-production lens I think falls under
the SRE umbrella so this also this I
think a couple of videos and maybe
articles where I've read where they
typically Define it as class SRE
implements devops that's one thing that
I've seen what's your take on that
that's a really interesting way of
putting it I think it's true to some
extent when I think about SRE it's like
when I think about Ops you know you you
can break it down into like
pre-production to production and
post-production like those three are all
totally fair parts of the system and I
think SRE generally lives in that kind
of post-prod environment where they're
defining those standards obviously like
those are the things you have to build
into your systems beforehand but mostly
they're thinking about okay once things
are live when things are out do we have
visibility are we doing the right things
and so I like to think most SRA teams
live in that world and so they it's kind
of like SRE implements
postprod Ops implements devops so maybe
like another tree down where in reality
it should be SRE implements devops
because you should be a working together
and being kind of working across the
stock so yeah I really like that that
way of putting it so the other question
I've been meaning to ask is that there's
a lot of confusion in the rules but
you've kind of broken it down for us
here but there's also these other new
roles that I keep seeing in many
companies for example this
infrastructure engineering or Cloud
engineer are these also like different
names for the same thing
I think it's another one of those cases
where there's still a lot of overlap so
like when I think about Cloud
engineering it's almost like pre-devops
like if devops is kind of focused on hey
how do we enable teams to to build our
code run their code get it into our
Cloud deploy it you know monitor things
like that then Cloud engineering is like
even more like one like one step behind
that it's like what is our Cloud where
are we building it what does it look
like how do we track it how do we like
are we using infrastructure as code like
setting the true foundations of
everything and like kind of like
building those Bare Bones stack and then
everything else kind of Builds on top of
that so I think that's where kind of
cloud engineering generally ends and I
think cloud engineering probably has
like that more of that pre-prod overlap
with with devops and then you know SRE
has like the post-prod overlap with
devops and so they're kind of living in
similar worlds but yeah Cloud
Engineering in my mind is more like
truly building that foundation and
enabling devops then do their job which
is then enabling developers to do their
job
and where do you think these things
differ so is it just on the environment
or anything else yeah I think it comes
down to the outcome so like when you
when you think about like building these
teams internally I think you had to take
a step back and say what exactly are we
trying to solve like what is the desired
outcome if your desired outcome is hey
our developers are not setting up
monitoring correctly they're you know
they're not maybe their pipeline doesn't
have enough automation for for setting
up that kind of stuff we have uptime
problems okay you're thinking about
reliability you got you need an SRE team
right even if there might be some
overlap with like what the devops team
is doing if your desired outcome is
reliability that's probably going to be
your first step if your problem is hey
we've got stuff all over TCP we have
things on app engine we've got things on
kubernetes we've got RDS we've got
people running things in kubernetes like
okay you got to take a step back and say
okay we have we have a weak Foundation
we need to build that Foundation First
okay you're probably going to look at
Cloud engineering and then you say like
okay we know we've kind of invested in
our Cloud we have some idea of how we're
doing it it's just really hard to get
there like we have kubernetes that's our
future but you know for a developer to
build their deployment get into
kubernetes moderate that's going to be
really hard okay you're probably
thinking about devops so I think taking
a step back and thinking about what is
the end goal and that will answer the
question of what do you need today yeah
I think that makes it a lot of sense so
I think sort of understanding your
outcome defines your rule is what
we get from this exactly and I think
that's where like a lot of teams
struggle is like they don't have those
clear Charters and I think the more
clearly you can Define the charter and
say like this is what success looks like
for a team the better those teams can
work because yeah devops is a very broad
space like SRE is very very Broad and so
even within that I think you have to
kind of give people that Charter and say
this is exactly what we care about like
is it you know we want more visibility
like we don't necessarily have uptime
issues but we don't know if we have
uptime issues okay layer Charter is
going to be a bit different it's like
enabling monitoring and observability
versus hey let's put together slos and
create that culture of monitoring
Excellence so like even within that
there's like different Charters and you
have to be very intentional about what
that Charter is so in your experience
what do you think about the team sizes
then would that again depend on your
your Charter go back to that and then
you decide yeah I think it really
depends on the charter I think you know
you probably want to start with smaller
teams to begin with like you don't want
to just bring on a team of like 10 sres
and then say like okay you guys are just
gonna go do everything because then that
a causes thrash for the SRE team but
then also thrash for the development
teams because they're saying hey
everyone's asking something different of
me like I have no idea what I'm doing so
be very intentional about like what what
your Charter is and then that kind of
dictates your team and obviously that
Charter might change over time right
like if you start today with like k-op
time is what we really care about we
have problems with that liability okay
you have a small team you know your
standard three to six people may be kind
of focused on that and then you have
some other issues around observability
and monitoring maybe that team kind of
splits in half and focuses it on it and
then you can start kind of growing that
team and have a team dedicated on
observability and monitoring and you
kind of see this I know organization
that I've been doing SRE for a while
like you look at startups that have Ava
100 to 300 people online drink team you
see like one dedicated SRE team that
just kind of does everything but you
look at companies that have more
established SRE foundations and you have
like you see like head of reliability
head of observability and like even
within that you have people that are
kind of running those individual
Charters so I think obviously teams are
not going to get there immediately so
don't try to do everything all at once
and build out too many teams start small
and kind of figure out where your
weaknesses are and hire around that I
think that
that mature is an organization you could
probably spend more time in reliability
and things like that whereas if you're
really just starting up then maybe your
your foundation is not good enough to
actually even know what you need to be
looking at I think that probably makes a
good segue into our next section where I
wanted to mainly talk about say tooling
the metrics and maybe the role
challenges so let's jump in like the
devops role like you said is something
that comes like earlier in the life
cycle in the development life cycle so
can you talk a little bit about the
tooling like you know you have this
build pipeline automation you have the
CI CD tooling how so what is all that
how does that play with these devops
principles yeah absolutely I think one
of the principles that I think is common
across everything is kind of like the
whole idea of like don't repeat yourself
the basic like software engineering
practices and not so much even from like
the devops team's own code but more from
like an engineering standpoint so think
about tooling I think obviously it
starts with your Source control right
like every team has to kind of make a
decision on that you probably if you're
hiring a devops team you're probably far
enough along where you've kind of tied
yourself to some version control system
or another but I think that's where it
really starts right it's like what is
our basic set of practices that we want
to enforce across our our Version
Control like do we want pull requests
approvals enabled for everything do we
want you know protected Master branches
things like that like what and maybe
you're not going to Define this up front
but you might set that as a long-term
goal say like if we do everything
correctly we can now get to this place
where people are shipping faster they're
emerging things their approvals are
happening whatever so I can set that
goal so it starts with the Version
Control and then once you have the
version control stuff set up then it
comes down to even like dependency
management system so are you using an
internal artifactory are you using you
know GitHub packages are you are you
using any of those because you don't
really ship any libraries internally
like what is your artifact store
internally so you know kind of starting
with that immediate step and then you're
going to think about not just dependency
management systems but then the actual
build pipelines and you know things like
Jenkins kind of action Circle CI what
are the requirements there and so
this is an interesting part because I
think the devops team also almost not
just thinks about tooling but they need
to be kind of product managers in some
sense but they're thinking about like
hey what are the things we need in order
to like support the rest of our
organization right it's like do you want
to do you have the capacity to build
like paralyzation and caching and all
this stuff yourself into your build
pipelines if not okay maybe maybe you're
not going to go with something like
something as Bare Bones as Jenkins and
you want to buy something off the shelf
right so kind of figuring out like what
is a use case like what kind of tools
are we building you know are we building
lots of really heavy Docker containers
are we just building small JavaScript
projects like what is a standard thing
you're doing because now you've got your
kind of build pipeline set up in place
and then your build pipeline is
obviously going to do a bunch of stuff
right it's like you're probably going to
do you're going to run tests you're
going to ideally take those to that test
coverage and ship it off somewhere so
you can track that so you're gonna
probably own like a sonar Cuban Sims or
something something similar to that
you're gonna also have you know whatever
your Cloud engineering team if if they
exist and if they've built something
like whatever that pipeline is to get
things into that system and so thinking
about that infrastructure there thinking
about alerting and Incident Management
so are you like if builds are failing
like is that something that's alertable
so are you going to be integrating with
your Incident Management tools like
sending that information in there are
you going to be integrating with slack
or teams or whatever to send information
to developers about those builds and so
all these kinds of things that I think
are part of that process is definitely
not necessarily owned by devops but it's
something that they need to have a lot
of say in and say like hey here's how
we're going to be consuming a lot of
those things and then this is where
we're kind of inching into like more of
the observable monitoring space is
obviously you're observing and
monitoring your actual build system and
pipelines all the tools that you run but
also things like build flakiness and
those kind of metrics where you want to
be tracking and giving that visibility
and so you have your own things that
you're going to be trying to get into
into the monitoring world and so I think
this is kind of like the General stock
that I think most devops teams are
working with and so kind of thinking
going back to what I was talking about
like don't repeat yourself I think as a
devops team is looking at there's a tire
stock they should be thinking about hey
how do we be abstract away a lot of our
stock and make it easy for developers to
consume it right so maybe you're not
opinionated on you know when things send
slack messages but you want to make it
easy for teams to say like okay if I
want to send a slack message from my
pipeline here's how I do it and so can
it give them the tools to do those
things that a makes it easy for
developers but B follows your own
practices so you're not maintaining now
like 15 versions of a slack messaging
system that's like sending messages over
right it's like you want to keep your
own life easier so like I think devops
teams as part of their stock should be
thinking about design principles and
things like that as well because it's
going to make their life hell in the
future if they don't do that from day
one yeah that really Rings very close to
my heart because I see that you know
like you say most devops teams come in
with the tooling as a religion and then
it just gets you know outdated or you
you don't have budgets for that and you
have to move to something else and then
the reason why you're doing it is
completely lost so yeah I think stepping
back and having abstraction is a is
great piece of advice yeah I think
that's why makes like great devops
devops engineers and sres and Cloud
Engineers is like almost having a
product hat you know I know like all
these roles are highly Technical and so
that's why I've seen like you know
really high functioning devops teams and
SRI teams sometimes they even have a
product manager and like embedded into
the team that is like extremely
technical because you are kind of your
customer is the internal development
team right like that is who your
customer is I start like we can talk
about sres customers which differs
slightly but like for the devops team
their customer is his development and so
if you have a customer then you should
be thinking about how do I enable them
to do their job like that is your
Charter at the end of the day right and
so really taking a step back and saying
how do I enable those teams to do their
best and I think having that lens having
that product hat on I think helps devops
Engineers kind of perform a lot better
and like I think it gives you visibility
into like hear the things that should be
working so you're not going off and
Building Things and wasting your own
time it helps you prioritize like these
are the most high impact things that I
could be doing and so I think that
product hat is super super important
that's very interesting because that was
one thing I had not really thought about
so yeah that's good to know so apart
from your traditional devops tooling
skill having a kind of ability to step
back abstract look at things at a little
bit higher level will make you
successful at your job exactly okay I
wanted to now switch gears to SRE and I
I think from the you know the site
reliability engineering book from Google
I remember this analogy which of course
as a mother or just completely made a
lot of sense I just want to talk about
that it says that the analogies between
software engineering and labor and
children so it says the labor before the
birth is painful and difficult but the
labor after the birth is where you
actually spend most of your effort and
so I just wanted to talking a little bit
about that quote which is so true in
real life but also in software
engineering or how do you think that
kind of comes into this SRE role do you
agree with that yeah I definitely think
so
really funny funny way of putting it but
I think it's totally true and I think
when I think about the work that goes in
before you know before production before
things are out like that to me and this
is kind of a broader note on SRE
generally I think that the thing that's
really hard about SRE is it's very much
like an influence role right like you're
not just building things but you need to
get people to care about it you need to
get people to do things like it's an
extremely difficult role for that
particular reason like not even
necessarily the technical side of things
which is challenging enough and
especially because SRA teams and most
organizations are operating at like you
know a one to Thirty to one to fifty
ratio for like SRE to regular product
engineering and so they're trying to
influence all these people to do things
and that I think that's where a lot of
the hard work really comes in and so
kind of thinking about the first part
like what is that initial upfront labor
it's like okay figuring out based on our
Charter again what are the things that
we don't have that we need in order to
get to a world where we can accomplish
our Target right it's not even like how
do we accomplish our Charter but how do
we get to a place where we could
reasonably figure out how to accomplish
our Charter and so that's where you're
setting up your monitoring and
observability stock you're doing things
like setting standards for tracing for
logging for metrics like everything kind
of has to be standardized you want
people to be doing things in similar
ways that way you can kind of things are
flowing into the right systems you have
reporting built on top of that and once
you have all this stuff kind of defined
then it's like you're running after
people and saying like hey like you're
still running you know our old tracing
system like can you please add the span
ID to your traces can you do X Y and Z
like you're trying to push other people
to do this I think that's where a lot of
that that pain comes from for sres is
like SRE is given this Charter to be
like hey can you make our company more
reliable right and that's fallen on the
SRE team but it's not really a charter
for the rest of the organization right
and like so SRE is trying to take their
Charter and make everyone else do it
because that's kind of what the role is
and so that's where a lot of that
initial upfront effort works is like
getting people to care about those
things and driving that visibility
because once you have that then it's a
matter of like okay we've kind of had
this foundation and so now we're seeing
what the problems are in order to get to
that final Charter and then it's like
same thing all over again and now you're
just like is that kind of whack them all
right it's like kind of like the raising
a child analogy he's like okay it's
there we got everything but now there's
like it needs so much more nurturing to
get to our final State and so it's like
okay we're gonna start small we're gonna
be like everyone needs to set up your
monitors okay you know we have monitors
okay now you're gonna set up a learning
you're gonna set up on Call okay you're
gonna connect your monitors to your
rotation you're gonna make sure you have
contacts you have you know so on and so
forth It's like you need that foundation
and like really push the organization to
get there and then you can start
nurturing the organization to get to
that final state so that's kind of how I
think about like those two those two
sides of the equation yeah I think like
when you talk about logging and yeah the
tracing I think it that is like an art I
would say it's almost like I mean maybe
it's a science sorry I should say that I
mean I think it's a it could be a book
in itself or a maybe a 100 but
consistent itself but yeah that's very
true but they're not switching into that
I think if I specifically come what
about the coming to the Matrix angle so
what would be the metrics that say the
devops teams look at versus SRE if you
could just can break it down for us yeah
absolutely so when I think about devops
teams like you're thinking about
developer productivity you know things
like that and so your metrics are going
to be more around like the actual
operational side of things like the
developer operation side of things so
things like build fake build flakiness
so like are there are issues with the
build system or they're like specific
repositories or services that are
causing a lot of build failures how do
we prevent that how do we detect that
kind of stuff because that is where a
lot of time goes away so actually taking
a step back when you think about devops
is like how much time are people like
developers spending like actually
writing code versus how much time are
they spending dealing with tooling right
and the more you can reduce the dealing
with tooling side of things the better
and so things like that things like time
to production it's another great one and
so this is where like you know the the
collaboration between devops and Cloud
engineering really comes into play is
like yeah it's a time for production
like is it easy for devops teams to get
things into the cloud platform but is it
easy for developers to kind of Traverse
their their systems into that so you
know time to code time to time to
production or time to whatever X
environment things like basic like build
times you know are there like are there
bottlenecks on the build systems so I
think those are the kinds of metrics
that devops teams are obviously looking
at I mean they have like monitoring type
metrics as well like if your Jenkins
goes down then obviously have a problem
so you're looking at similar metrics and
logs and things like that from your
systems but the things that you own are
more of these kind of like operational
metrics that tell you like hey are we
are we accomplishing our Charter in that
same way and so I think it's it's
interesting in that SRE I mean devops
kind of owns certain sets of metrics
that necessarily like SRE on the other
side doesn't own a metric in the same
way right they can't impact their own
metrics like if SRE is looking at uptime
as like their final goal or like you
know their slos and what they're
breaching at the end of the day like
they can only tell developers like hey
you're a service and it's breaching the
threshold and we're going to page you or
whatever but like an SRA team can't do
anything about it versus devops kind of
owns their own metrics like they have
these kind of things that they are going
to push forward word I think that's some
of the slight differences there between
like the devops on the SRE side okay
interesting so the metrics can actually
help devops teams get better whereas SRE
even if they look at the metrics they
dependent on somebody else to fix it
exactly I think that's where like the
pain comes for the SRE side where it's
like again it's like an influence job
like you can only tell people okay
something is wrong with your service and
here's how here's what we're seeing but
you can't do anything about it versus
devops again that product lens right
it's like you have not just like
technical metrics but you have like
business metrics or like these kind of
like kpis right it's like that's the
interesting thing and you might have a
whole bunch of slis underneath that but
you're tracking against like business
metrics you're not just looking at like
uptime or whatever like more like
technical things so I think I'll maybe
I'll ask you to also explain SLO and SLI
again for us you know just to make sure
everybody's on the same page yeah
absolutely so I think when you think
about slos slos are your actual
objective right it's like hey we are
trying to get to
like you know 99 up time or whatever
like things like that so that is your
final objective the SLI is like an
indicator that tells you am I meeting my
objective that's the simplest way I like
to describe it as like the SLO is
literally what are we trying to
accomplish and the SLI is like the
indicator that tells us if we are doing
that so your uptime metric could be your
SLI and your SLO is the target so you
have like I have a 99 uptime SLO the SLI
is like the uptime indicator like what
is our current uptime like what is it
looking like over time that's kind of
how I think about SLO and SLI and then
you have slas which are more of like the
actual agreements or promises so you
might have like a six nines or like
let's say you have a three nines SLA so
you're committed to a customer that you
have a three nine SLA from uptime your
SLO might be four nines because that's
your objective because if you meet that
and internally you're tracking correctly
against your agreement your legally
binding agreement with the customer and
your SLI is going to be the actual like
indicator that says how are we doing
against our uptime what is our current
uptime so that's kind of like telling us
where we're going
so in this thing where we have a service
level agreements for sres I mean with
the customer which is your end user do
we have something similar for devops
like end user is the developers can the
developers say this is the agreement I
want uh oh no is that more a
collaborative effort just
yeah that's a great question I think the
best engineering organizations view that
those internal relationships as
extremely collaborative and I think
there needs to be collaboration between
all of those teams and this is kind of
like you know a whole topic of its own
because I think what engineering
organizations should not do is like
create silos between SRE and devops and
development like those teams should all
work hand in hand right it's like okay
your devops team is kind of thinking
putting their product hat and they're
thinking with and talking to developers
and saying hey what are the areas of
friction how do we make it easier for
you to build things and just focus on
that value right and if your SRA team is
thinking about yeah like how do we get
people to do their monitors and their
dashboarding and all this stuff but
you're thinking about those two like why
is like SRE kind of pigeonholed into
post-production like in theory those
things could be automated for you as
well right like if you are following a
standard framework and you generate new
projects out of that framework and then
you have a standard logging system and
you have a standard metric system in
theory your initial framework and your
initial build could generate all the
same things that need to get into like
your SRE team cares about so your SRE
team and your devops team should then
work together and say hey I'm the SRA
team these are the things that we need
our developers to be doing you know
before they go into production how much
of that can we automate for developers
as part of their pre-prod systems right
are there things that the build pipeline
could be doing is like tagging your
images with certain shots or whatever so
that that flows into our monitoring are
there like things we can build into
their software templates that's going to
do logging the right way and so SRE and
devops should be working together to say
hey devops like can you guys help us do
our jobs better from day one so we're
not like scrambling afterwards right and
the same thing between like the cloud
platform and the devops teams like
devops team saying hey here's what our
current status quo is like this is what
we need from you in order to like do our
jobs better so like how do we figure out
like how we're structuring our platform
so it's going to be a lot easier you
know things like that and so I think all
of those teams especially should be
collaborating between each other and
that's going to make the developers life
a lot easier so imagine like the dream
dream world where you know a developer
comes in they don't necessarily know
what all the the underlying
infrastructure is right it's like maybe
on kubernetes it doesn't really matter I
come in I have a set of software
templates I say okay I want to create a
spring boot service and I go into
whatever our internal portal is I select
a spring boot template boom it creates a
repository for me with the same settings
that devops recommends it generates the
code that code is already pre-configured
with the right logging structure is
configured with the right monitors it's
going to get set up it's configured with
the right build pipeline that integrates
with what devops already set up it's
integrated with sonar Cube and the
metrics are already going there boom I
write my code I merge into the master
deploy pipeline picked it up it goes
into our infrastructure metrics are
starting to flow into whatever
monitoring tool you're using you've got
your metrics set in place as developer
all I did was I just followed this
template and I did a couple of things
and everything just magically works like
that's the dream land that we can get to
and the only way you can get there is if
all of those teams are collaborating
with each other really really closely
and all of them are kind of wearing
their products hats thinking like this
is not just a technical problem it's
about how do we as an engineering
organization deliver faster for our end
customer users and so I think that's
kind of what injury organizations should
be striving to so actually in a way all
of us should be working on that SLE with
the end user exactly yeah everyone
should own that just to some extent yeah
that's great I wanted to ask you also in
terms of roles when we go back to it
role called a system admin is that now
dead we don't see that at all right yeah
I think that's kind of Gone by the
wayside I think you still see that some
organizations where if you have Legacy
infrastructure that you need to operate
in some ways then like that kind of
falls under the cloud platform-ish teams
and so I think that's kind of merged
into like depending on where you lived
as a system admin you might go more into
like the cloud platform engineering team
or you might be more on the devops side
I think there's not really any overlap
with the SRE side of things but you know
if you if you're like CIS admitting
skills or around like yeah pipelines and
build systems and being able to like you
know things like that that stuff you
might go more into the devops side of
things like if you're like a like a
heavy Unix person and you've got you
know all your commands and you can kind
of figure out networking and those kinds
of things you're going to be a great
fight for cloud platform engineering
like that's probably like the future
there so I think it's like CIS admin was
kind of a very broad role it's like hey
we've got these like Mega machines and
we have no idea what the hell those
systems are doing and we need somebody
that's like can you next girl to figure
it out but now it's like okay we've got
specialized teams that have those
Charters so you can kind of figure out
like what exactly you want to be doing
and really focusing in on that and would
it be that from that similar context
would it be easier for a if a developer
wants to go to a devops or an SRE role
would it be a better fit for SRE or say
devops
I think it's interesting again because
what we usually see is a lot of
developers really care or specialize in
one of those there's people that really
care about infrastructure they love like
they come into like a young organization
things are starting to get a bit hairy
and it's like hey I'm gonna take a week
I'm gonna set up terraform right now set
up infrastructure as code I'm going to
set up our vpcs whatever it's like
that's going to make my life easier it's
going to make me a lot happier so I'm
going to go and do that infrastructure
stuff okay you're probably going more
towards Cloud platform engineering at
that point right so that's kind of like
one set of Engineers and then another
set of Engineers are like oh my God the
Bill's taking forever like we gotta you
know go in fix that to fix those systems
like everyone's doing things differently
I hate our like lack of standardization
I want to bring some sort of like
standards and you know order to the
chaos probably more like this like
devopsy type space and then there's some
people that really care about monitoring
and uptime and standards and tracing and
like logging and like that kind of stuff
it's like they kind of freak out if
you're like I have no idea what's going
on in production like I have no
visibility like I feel like I can't
sleep but night because I don't know
what's gonna happen okay you're probably
more like leaning to that SRE space so I
think what we see is like developers
usually have like one passion area that
they they really you know really really
like or they spend a lot of time in and
so I think that kind of naturally they
have a path to those those worlds what
about you know this ability to there are
certain Engineers who come in as uh
devops Engineers so they have this
ability to write custom Scripts things
to do all the automation so is that a
big skill to have in both these spaces
or only say devops yeah I would say I
think very
solid like software engineering skills
when it comes to like coding probably is
more required on like Cloud platform
engineering and devops because yeah like
you're going to be hacking things
together you've got a bunch of systems I
got to talk to each other like you're
more active in that space so I think
generally speaking like you need to be
good at coding not necessarily like
system design or architecture or things
like that like the high level
abstraction and I think that's where
we're like we're not going to devops or
Cloud platform engineering is coming
into like a software engineering role
that's kind of where like they're really
good at writing code but maybe you need
to take a step back and like think about
like software design principles in some
cases SRE is kind of the inverse where
like you don't necessarily have to be
like an amazing coder you know but you
need to be able to think about like the
systems and how they interact and more
of like that architectural side of
things and so I think that's where their
skill set is and so maybe not so much
time I knew shoved like Hey how do I get
get up action to talk to our Legacy
Jenkins build just part of our
Recreation and all like that stuff is
like probably like doing the weeds for
like an SRE team but they're thinking
more about like Hey how do our systems
interact where the bottlenecks the
critical areas of risk and so there's
definitely like some overlapping skill
set but that's kind of where I see SRE
teams have most of their thinking hats
on okay so more of the details on the
system interactions and things like that
and how your systems talk to each other
would be devops and taking a step back
and looking at flows to see where
bottlenecks are would be SRE exactly
okay I now want to switch gears a bit
into say the communication angle so one
of the things that is interesting from
SRE is and I guess it's also in devops
is when the incident occurs they do this
thing called as blame free postmortems
can you explain that I believe from at
the book on the SRE I mean the site
reliability engineering from Google they
talk a lot more about this but is it a
similar concept also for devops yeah I
definitely think so like I think if
there's an issue with how somebody has
set up their pipelines or they're not
integrating with you tooling the right
way or whatever I think your first
question should be what was the Gap
right like was there a Gap in our
tooling that said like hey I need to go
off and build my own thing because like
the current systems that we provided
don't work right like what is the reason
why the developer like went off the rail
somewhere it went off like outside of
those guard Wheels to go and do
something that the devops team hadn't
kind of given their stamp to that should
be our first question again going back
to like the product hat right it's like
don't blame the user like there might be
something wrong right it's like is there
something that we should be working on
that's kind of step one step two is like
okay maybe if there was no thing then
why did they kind of go down that path
right like was it a lack of evangelism
you know like what did they not know
that these systems existed do they not
like fully understand it okay if that's
the case then maybe there needs to be
more like education within the
organization right taking opportunities
for lunch and learn thinking
opportunities for internal guides or
wikis that talk about the stuff maybe
there should be automated tooling and
you know the kind of thinking about what
are the process things that went wrong
to get here and so again it's not about
blaming the folks that did something
quote unquote wrong but understanding
how do we make sure that doesn't happen
again because like sure you can blame
someone all you want but you're gonna
hire somebody else somebody else is
going to do the same thing again and
you're just going to keep blaming
everybody you're going to figure out
like Hey how do we as a team just accept
that this is going to happen and make
sure that we have processes in place to
ensure that it doesn't how do we make
sure that we are able to accomplish our
Charter outside of what those teams are
doing right that's kind of what it comes
down to like blame free postmortems as
well it's like things are going to
happen incidents will always happen no
matter how brilliant of a programmer you
are and that's right team you are
something is going to go wrong and so
when something goes wrong you want to
take a step back and say like okay
something went wrong doesn't matter who
did it how do we make sure this doesn't
happen again like that's always a
question is like how do we prevent
something like this what were the gaps
right it's like we know what's going to
happen and we need to make sure it
doesn't and so the devops team should be
thinking about it the same way it's like
we know it's going to happen again how
do we make sure it doesn't and so I
think taking that lens is super
important and I think there's more of a
collaboration element here as well where
they need to be working with developers
and say like Hey how do we make sure
like that doesn't happen again like what
can we be doing in order to better
enable you and so yeah I think blame
free culture I think is just important
generally and like I think devops should
be taking that kind of like product lens
again when they see these kinds of
issues on okay why are people not doing
the things that we hope they should be
doing that's interesting when you talk
about the collaboration angle and so
this question might be a little bit
long-winded but one of the things I
noticed is whenever we have an incident
and when you do this root cause analysis
then there is of course uh analysis done
on what really happened which maybe the
SRE team looks at and then a ticket is
created and then that either goes to say
devops or a developer team in and then
there's almost like even though we know
that there should not be a blame free
culture but then it almost looks like
this work is like given to different
teams and then there's this problem of
you know like you said before operating
in silos right so that again then
there's this problem there and so I
almost wonder do we need to have a kind
of a facilitator role as well to have
this kind of blame-free post-mortem and
how does communication play with all
these different roles yeah I think when
it comes to like postpartum specifically
like in theory the facilitator should be
SRE and then it's kind of like kind of a
conflict of interest but that falls
under their Charter rights like if their
goal is to make they improve uptime or
improve reliability like doing good
postmortems falls into that world right
it's like the better you can do your
postpartums the better you can follow
those action items that are coming out
of it the better you're going to be in
terms of
you know accomplishing your own Charter
so it's in your best interest to enable
other teams to do the things that they
need to do in order to accomplish their
own Charter again kind of going back to
the idea that SRE is like an influence
organization and so when you think about
like doing a postmortem you want to be
facilitating those conversations and say
like hey did SRE provide you the tooling
to say something went wrong like were
you able to detect it in time were you
alerted in time like where the
foundational piece is missing and if so
we're going to take those action items
back and fix them because that's our job
right that's kind of on our systems and
then facilitating those action items and
say like here is the clearer outcomes of
this postpartum right like somebody had
to take charge and say like okay out of
this push boredom there's like five
action items and in theory like I think
what happens in a lot of cases is you
create these jira tickets there's like
15 tickets that come out of a
post-mortem and there's no
prioritization in place like nobody
they're just they're just there in the
void and you know people either take
them or they don't and that's like a
it's like the classic thing that happens
with these postmortems right so I think
coming out of a postpartum the SRE team
should be saying like hey we can't leave
this post mortem is not over until we
have an idea of prioritization right
it's like which of these things are
must-haves which of these things are
should have some which of these things
are nice to have and so the must-haves
are going to be like hey we are going to
bother you incessantly until we know
this must have they're Complete because
those are kind of what you have agreed
to say like okay these are things that
have to be fixed now and we've kind of
all agreed on this within this
postmortem this should have for
something you probably want to track
somewhere it's like hey are we building
up they should have like how do we
continuously go back to the developing
teams and say like hey we need your help
to prioritize these things and so I
think yeah the SR team kind of plays
that facilitator role a little bit but
it also comes down to like those
engineering managers on the development
teams as well right it's like if you're
an engineering manager if you're a
product manager you can't lose track of
the fact that you are working closely
with the SRA team right you are enabling
the SRE team to do their Charter right
like if you are just like hey screw you
guys like we're just gonna go off and do
our own thing you're not creating a good
working environment internally so as an
engineering manager or product manager
it is your job to kind of go back and
say like Hey how do we as our team help
our fellow sibling teams to do their
jobs as well so like we're going to do
our best and they're going to do their
best I think that's the kind of General
agent culture you want to create but
yeah the SRE team I think is like a
facilitator within the post-mortem
boundary itself
yeah that's interesting because I read
this article which said that the SRE
practice involves contributions to like
every level of the organization I think
that probably makes sense because they
are then playing that facilitator role
right because they'll talk to I guess
the product owners the developers the
engineering managers and then yeah and I
guess the devops teams do have this
communication so would you say that so
this is another skill set for an SRE a
good communication skills absolutely
yeah I think it goes back to like yeah
sorry is an influence role right it's
like influence in many cases when an SRA
team has formed it was probably because
you are starting to see reliability as
like a key business driver right like
there's a reason why you're investing
nobody's going to invest in reliability
it doesn't matter right and it's there's
like some key business reason why you're
investing in reliability enough time and
things like that and so usually that's
it that team falls under the VP
engineering or the CTO directly it's
like you know the development team for
the SRA team kind of directly reports up
into the VP engineering and so there's
like a clear line of communication there
but then you also have kind of
visibility into the rest of the
organization and you need to influence
the rest of their organization and so
being able to communicate to leadership
where the bottlenecks are and like what
you need resources and help in kind of
driving across the org as well as
communicating directly to engineers and
within your own team I think that's kind
of like a unique skill set that sres
need to have because in some cases it's
like the SRA team cannot necessarily
directly influence the engineering team
directly and they almost need to say
like hey you know vpe like here's what
we need from the origin organization we
know it's a broader effort but here's
why it's important and we need your help
in order to like make this a key
initiative it's just kind of like an up
to go out type of a model and I mean you
see this in a few other functions as
well like security is a great example of
this where security is like okay guys
figure out how you're going to make our
software more secure and they're trying
to get developers to do things and like
they're trying to communicate up to the
CSO whatever and that's kind of a
similar thing where it's like I go up to
go out type of a system and so SRE is
very similar in that case where it's
like you need to be able to communicate
up you need to be able to communicate
out you're going to figure out how
you're gonna to drive that influence and
so there's definitely a lot of
communication involved and it's not the
first thing you think about when you
think about SRE but it's like I think
that's where a lot of people go into SRE
kind of have that initial shock is like
there's a lot more like people stuff
going on in this role than you would
initially expect like it's not just a
technical role it's one of the fun
things about the role as well but it's
definitely thing that people don't
realize as you go into it okay that's
good to know and I guess now moving on
to the sort of the last bit of the
section on this episode I want to talk a
little bit on the day-to-day life of an
SRE versus a devops as you would see it
so what would a good day for an SRE look
like okay for an SRE you're probably
riding a doc somewhere on like your
future State on you know what liability
looks like there's no incidents
monitoring and metrics are flowing
beautifully there's no postmortems all
the action items are empty there's
nothing in jira that's a beautiful day
for an SRE now well does that ever
happen probably not but like a more
realistic day I think is a combination
of kind of like yeah goal setting like
kind of thinking about doing analysis on
the metrics that you were accountable
for like uptime and saying okay where
are the issues are there things that are
popping up that we don't really know
about who should we be talking to about
these things I think it's probably part
of your day another part of your day is
probably talking to other engineering
teams and talking to them about slos and
adoption and things like that that's
gonna be part of your day another part
is a evangelizing things so you're
probably defining like SRE Readiness
standards and things like that and you
know communicating that to the rest of
the organization one thing we didn't
talk about at all is like the kind of
initial SRE concept of like being the
initial on-call team as well so like I
think there was like a period of time in
which SRE was also the first line of
defense like they would be on call for
things and then they would escalate it
to engineering teams what's interesting
is we don't really see that as often
these days I know Google still kind of
does things that way but it's more of
like a you build it you own it type of
model and most organizations now and so
I would say like in some organizations
and sres day to day might be like Yeah
by Fielding the pager or whatever like
being on call for things that are like
not their own things but things that
other people have built but yeah we
don't really see that happening as often
these days especially at companies that
are like sub thousand Engineers but it's
mostly like yeah the teams are going to
be on call for the things that they own
and maybe there's a separate like
support team that's on call generally
that's going to be escalating things
through the pipe but yeah I think that's
kind of generally the day-to-day is like
a bit of yeah you're standing like
observability monitoring Incident
Management you know know being part of
these ongoing issues being that sounding
more the postmortem facilitator the
incident facilitator evangelism and the
kind of like goal setting and working
with the devops and the cloud
engineering teams and things like that
so those are kind of like the things
that we usually see in like a general
day to day okay and I guess like you
said so a bad day would be if
party if I was the first line of defense
to have a bad David and other things but
would it be more stressful if I was you
know so almost like the first line of
defense yeah I think I think that's why
it would get really bad but I think you
can still have a very bad day if there's
this incidents generally across your
organization because like we talked
about like the SRE team is kind of the
facilitator so they are still operating
as part of those incidents they're being
not standing for they're facilitating it
they're looping in the right people you
know they're making sure that their
systems are looking good they're making
sure that the right data is being
provided to the team so they can make
clear decisions they're providing
insight into like the escalation
escalation path escalation policies so
they're kind of like not in all cases
but in many cases they're kind of like
running that Incident Commander type
role as well so they're kind of in
charge because yeah that incident is
like directly affecting their final
metric which is like uptime or
reliability whatever and so it's in
their best interest to run that incident
as smoothly as possible and so
regardless of whether like the first
line engineer where they they are
triaging and resolving incidents from
the get-go or whether you're like it's a
viewability you own it type of a model
you're still involved with those
incidents and you're still trying to
figure out and help those teams and so
on top of everything else you're trying
to do I think that's gonna be a bad day
another example of a bad day is like
you're trying to get people to do things
but you don't have any say into it and
like other teams are saying hey we've
got these deadlines we've got these
other things we're working on like our
manager says we don't have time for this
and you're just blocked like you just
can't do anything because you're blocked
on everyone else and I think that's
almost the most frustrating thing where
it's like I am not able to do my job
because I I'm not getting that buy-in
from other organizations and no fault of
their own either right it's like they
have their own things that they have to
be working on like their managers and
director whatever telling them this is
your priority like ignore reliability
doesn't matter but it's like no no
liability matters like that's what
matters to us it's like how do you kind
of cross those boundaries and so I think
a really bad days when that
collaboration breaks down right like and
it happens in every organization and you
need to be working on that I think that
can be a very like emotionally draining
bad day because like you just can't do
what you're trying to accomplish so I
think those are some examples of what
bad days can be okay great I think yeah
that kind of really drove home the point
where yeah you could get terribly
frustrated if you can't really do your
job because it depends on someone else
yeah exactly I think they obviously I
have to ask you now what a bad day for a
devops engineer looks like is it just
that see if GitHub is not working or is
down or say as your devops is download
Jenkins is down is that a bad day yeah I
would say like when the actual things
that you own are down like that's you
know kind of a bad day for everyone and
it's like you build a owner type thing
again like you own those systems the
systems are down and your developers are
are like what the hell I can't do
anything that's probably a really bad
day for Developers for for the devops
teams but another like lesser thought
about bad days like when you hear
frustrations from developers like kind
of just generally it's like it's not
working for me like this sucks like I'm
not able to build like it's super flaky
whatever it's like the thing that you're
building or not working for teams and I
think that can be really frustrating
again from an emotional way it's like
okay whatever we're trying to do is not
working and like are we're not able to
enable those teams I think again like
this is where for both the SRE and like
they've obviously like that product had
like if you're a product manager for a
consumer app and you hear consumers
saying like this product sucks like I
want to use it like I'm going to churn
whatever like that's what sucks because
the product magic is the decisions that
we made clearly are not working or like
we're not able to execute on our on our
goals and you know I guess in the
consumer app people might churn in this
case like obviously people aren't going
to turn but like they're going to
complain or like you're gonna feel that
frustration kind of bubbling up and you
may not be able to do anything about
that so I think that can be a bad day is
like you're working on things and it's
not working correctly for teams you're
not enabling teams the right way there's
some Gap in like you know what you
thought was going to be the right path
forward I think those days could be like
very emotionally taxing and emotionally
like a bad day for devops teams and come
back on a positive note and a good day
would be where nobody's complaining yeah
well like things are just happening and
you see a lot of activity and like your
people are building things people are
deploying things everything's just
magically happening new projects are
being created and nobody has any
questions for you nobody has any feature
requests for you that means you've
almost like taken yourself out of the
equation you know it's like you build a
system in which people can operate
without the guidance of devops and
everything is just working seamlessly I
think that's a wonderful day it's like
hey the stuff we're building is working
and teams are enabled and teams are off
just building things and doing things
for the business as opposed to like
grappling with infrastructural things so
I think that can be a really really
satisfying day for devops teams please
and now that you've laid all of this out
for us who do you think gets paid more
is it an SRE or a devops I think
nowadays it's starting to kind of get a
bit more equal I think what we see is
like devops teams can be a bit more
Junior in some cases so I think that's
where some of the paid disparity comes
is like you can probably get somebody
kind of fresh out of college a new grad
who has some coding experience you can
train them to be a good devops engineers
and so you can kind of get away with the
fewer like Junior folks whereas SRE
teams are a bit more experienced they
need to understand where bottleneck can
be and best practices and all that stuff
and so I think that's why on average you
see SRA teams might be being paid more
but I think it's because you know devops
teams in a lot of cases just have
slightly more Junior folks across the
board but I think you know once you're
kind of made a career on both you're
probably at the same pay grade okay so
that's interesting because I wanted to
ask you about you know the carrier
progression for uh sorry was
devops would I be writing saying that
after a point maybe would there be a
stagnation for a devops or is that not
the case yeah I think it depends on the
organization like if devops is kind of
just working Within These pipelines or
whatever it's like there's not much more
you can do like maybe you can get into
management and stuff and so I think it
really depends on the organization
because in some cases it's like there's
paths to I mean it could like devops
could live in the broader like developer
experience developer productivity orgs
and so it's like one piece of that and
so kind of going up into like running or
being a part of like the broader
developer experience team or being kind
of in charge of that I think is like
your career progression we're seeing a
lot more developer experience and
developer productivity teams coming up
in more organizations so I think they're
starting to be like an even more clear
path for devops folks so I think that's
one career path but at other
organizations sometimes it might be like
moving more into like platform or Cloud
engineering you know going up the ranks
there or like I think like maybe sres I
think that's where kind of like people
have a bad taste in their mouth for
devops I think that's why people are
trying to like Rebrand it or rename it
into all these other org speakers
because in some cases yeah devops have
been styling because it's your
organizations haven't really thought
about that Charter like why do we have a
devops team it's for a developer
experience and productivity and
efficiency so like why not give devops
the opportunity to own that entire thing
and so that's why it's like yeah we're
kind of calling it like developer
experience and things like that now and
so yeah I think if you are your
organization where there's just devops
and they don't own anything else then
yeah it's probably going to kind of
stagnate but yeah if you have the right
opportunity and the devops team is
within the right organization there's a
really great path there
that's very interesting so everything
kind of ties back to the Charter so even
I think so if your Charter is clear and
so as you get more mature then maybe the
carrier progression is also better for
the devops teams and exactly exactly
that's great ties in very well with how
we started uh sorry so I I guess the
next question would be do you see many
other roles that emerge from these roles
in the future yeah I definitely think so
like I think from an SRE standpoint you
probably see people starting to
specialize in individual parts of SRE so
things like we're already starting to
see that and the people who are really
good at monitoring and observability
people who are really good at kind of
like standards and governance and
compliance and things like that you know
people that are really good at like
internet management so maybe you might
have like people that kind of specialize
in that and so as we learn more about
these roles I think we are going to see
more specialization around there and so
I think that's something that for sure
we'll see and then I think in terms of
like the devops side of things you know
you're probably going to see
specialization in specific parts of
developer experience right so it's going
to be things like you know are you
working on like internal developer
portals are you working on you know
observability and metrics for a
developer experience side of things
you're working on pipelines like are you
going to be a product manager within
devops right like I mean we talked about
that like it is a product hat so is that
going to be a thing as well so I think
all of those things are examples of
where like we might see like a lot more
specialization and individual roles kind
of being carved out of these broader
spaces okay so yeah I think you talked
about something called developer
productivity there are organizations
which have a team that does that is it
okay yeah like their products I think is
what we see a lot of because like I
think they finally realize like hey this
is the charter right our Charter is to
make developers more productive and like
enable them to focus on building the
stuff that actually matters and so I
think that's what we're starting to see
now is like okay if we acknowledge that
that's a charter let's call the team
data it's developer productivity and all
these things kind of fall under
developer productivity okay it's like
the foundation for just general product
development work I'm so starting to see
more organizations build about the team
and again yeah it just goes back to the
Charter being a lot more clear and also
in terms of you also talked about things
like observability and roles coming from
there that's also very interesting do
you see actually things that exist today
like do you have like an observability
team I'm just curious about that because
yeah we see that all the time a large
organization so not necessarily at a
cortex but like we see like a lot of our
customers they have folks that are like
specialized in observability and
monitoring because in a large
organization you might have many tools
that are all kind of flowing and
generating data on your different types
of metrics and you want to report on
things and you want those like that
stuff to float in a single place you
want to set standards on how you're
doing monitoring and alerting there was
so many things that fall into that
umbrella it's like hey we're just going
to have a team of people that are
full-time thinking about this and doing
this versus like trying to have them do
like 20 different things because if if
your focus isn't more around like yeah
kind of like the slos and the adoption
and the best practices and you know
things like that you're not gonna have
time to think about the minutia the
nitty-gritty of like monitoring stack as
a whole and so it's like we're gonna
give that team in my Charters like
anything modern related that's you guys
that go figure that stuff out so it's
all boiling down to the Charter Ganesh
so it all comes after that so I have to
ask you is that a role in itself for the
future writing challenge
I think a good executive leadership team
I think that's what they should be doing
like you think about a good VP
engineering or a good CTO is like coming
in and setting that that Charter I think
truly everything comes down to that it's
like when you hire an SRA team you tell
them here is exactly what's wrong today
and here's the future we want to get to
and give them the autonomy to go and get
to that final world right and I think
that's my problem with kind of like this
whole idea of okrs is like key results
right it's like you're gonna give them
like oh we want these metrics to go up
by X percent okay cool maybe the worst
of a larger organization but if you're
building your SRE team from the ground
up it's more gonna be like here's our
final end State and you you as a team
figure out how you're going to get us
there and hold yourself accountable to
that that doesn't mean like not having
key results to the meaning there's no
accountability but like you need to help
them to find that vision for how they're
going to get there and so I think that's
why that Charter is so important even
things for like slos right it's like you
know a lot of organizations will come in
it's like oh Google does these slos
we're going to do the same thing but if
you're a smaller team like maybe your
slos are not necessarily like uptime
driven right your slos might be hey we
have a payment system and our payment
fraud rate is X Y and Z and so we want
to drive that particular rate down and
that is our business service objective
right like that's kind of some of the
things we want to think about so SRE
team should be given that again like if
the organization has a charter SRE team
can say like okay how do we get and
enable teams to find get to that state
and so I think you know that's what you
see in a really high performing
organizations every team knows why their
team is important and what their goal is
and they can just work towards that with
autonomy I think that's why it's super
important to have the starters and I
think that that role really follows at
the very top you know like leadership
needs to be setting those goals at a
very high level and then needs to
trickle down as well so yeah I think
that's where the charters really start
so I guess if I want to summarize this
whole thing apart from say the devops
versus SRE debate that we started it off
with like some of the key areas that I'm
seeing is that we need to like that
final SLA like everybody should be
looking at that so that's one angle
having a good Charter and I think this
whole communication piece comes from
strong leadership I think that's one big
thing but how do you also trickle that
down to these individual teams who are
operating how do you find that purpose
is that something to put the
recommendation then be that you go for
like customer workshops or something
like that like you see what the end user
does with even people who are like down
in the usually down in the hierarchy and
for them to get a feel of you know that
what their work is is important how do
you kind of in your experience how do
you get that Vision driven down to them
yeah I think a lot of it comes down to
like cross-team communication
communication upwards as well and so
like as an SRA team if either something
that you really want to drive right you
want to take a step back and say hey how
does it affect the bottom line like
maybe there's a convocation element to
it like we're seeing you know X hours
being spent on incident resolution and
if we had more visibility or automation
around automatic incident resolution it
would save X hours and so this is why
investing in this infrastructure and
this monitoring and tooling is going to
be super important it drives X percent
injury and cost and so again now your
leadership understands why that's super
important and how that gets you to your
Charter and then they can then
communicate that to the rest of Oregon
you can say like Hey we're not just
doing things for the sake of doing
things here is like the impact right you
want to always Define that if we do X
here is going to be the future state
right it's like you can't just go to
other teams and be like we need you to
do X they don't understand that right it
all comes down to that collaboration
this is just basic communication
practices as well right like if you're
an engineer working in a product team
you don't want your product manager to
say like here's a ticket like go
implement it right it's like here's what
we're trying to do here's how this like
helps us get to that final State and
then as a developer you feel like hey
I'm part of a bigger thing I have this
impact I understand why I'm doing the
things I'm doing or why this is super
important for their broader organization
and I think devops SRE is no different
you can just say like here's what we're
doing here's like we need everyone to
migrate on the circle CI like oh my God
like I've got like 15 other tickets I'm
working on like you can't just tell me
that it's like hey it's because we're
seeing a lot of whatever build failures
and we think that these particular
features are going to help us get there
and therefore that's going to help you
by reducing you know your recycle time
on PRS like you want to have that
communication and even when we talk
about like cortex and developer portals
which is what we do we tell people
saying like hey if I had a developer
portal I could do X like set that vision
and say like here's why we're doing this
and then you can get people bought it
and say like oh my God that future end
State sounds awesome like how can we
help you get there right it's like the
more you can set that like final end
goal and a very concrete end goal the
easier it's going to be for people to
feel like hey I know why I'm doing the
stuff I'm doing like it is high impact
it's meaningful so you can just give
people things to do but you got to tell
them here's why we're doing it and
here's the impact you're gonna have so I
think if I were to end it so apart from
the charter there's also data which you
as a concrete way of looking at it right
so exactly Charter have concrete data to
like you know bind to the Charter and
then you can have all the magic and have
a good communication and build a
successful platform
exactly yeah it's great it's been very
enlightening for me for Ganesh
personally and I hope it is for the
listeners of the show as well and before
I let you go I wanted to find out where
can people reach you if they wanted to
contact you would it be on Twitter or
LinkedIn yeah if you're interested in
hearing more about the stuff obviously
this is what I do for for a living is
working with all these teams and helping
them accomplish their Charters so you
can shoot me an email uh Ganesh
cortex.io and hopefully I will find it
in my box okay we'll do that I'll also
add a link to your Twitter and Linkedin
on the show notes apart from the other
references so thank you for coming on
the show thank you so much for having me
cleat this is Priyanka raghavan for
software engineering video thanks for
listening
thanks for listening to SC radio an
educational program brought to you by
Tripoli software magazine for more about
the podcast including other episodes
visit our website at se.radio.net
to provide feedback you can comment on
each episode on the website or reach us
on LinkedIn Facebook Twitter or through
our slack Channel at SC radio dot
slack.com you can also email us at team
sc-radio.net
this and all other episodes of SC radio
is licensed under created Commons
license 2.5
thanks for listening
[Music]